export const ECONOMICSA2016 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. Human wants are insatiable because wants are",
A: "limited while means are scarce.",
B: "unlimited and means are also unlimited.",
C: "limited and means are also limited.",
D: "unlimited while means are scarce.",
answer: "D. unlimited while means are scarce.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. Scale of preference is important for the following reasons except in",
A: "satisfying wants.",
B: "making rational choice.",
C: "making optimum allocation of resources.",
D: "using scarce resources efficiently.",
answer: "A. satisfying wants.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. In a socialist economy, prices of commodities are determined by",
A: "forces of demand and supply.",
B: "producers of the commodities.",
C: "the central planning authority.",
D: "consumers who are sovereign.",
answer: "C. the central planning authority.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. Which of the following cannot be classified as land in economics?",
A: "Bauxite deposit in the ground",
B: "A lake used for irrigation",
C: "A bulldozer for clearing farm land",
D: "Grazing field for cattle",
answer: "C. A bulldozer for clearing farm land",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. If the budget of the country was  7,200.00, ℎ𝑜𝑤 𝑚𝑢𝑐ℎ 𝑖𝑠 𝑎𝑙𝑙𝑜𝑐𝑎𝑡𝑒𝑑 𝑡𝑜 𝑒𝑑𝑢𝑐𝑎𝑡𝑖𝑜𝑛?",
A: "2,400.00",
B: "1,200.00",
C: "2,000.00",
D: "1,000.00",
answer: "A. 2,400.00",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. What is the ratio of expenditure on Health to Agriculture?",
A: "2:3",
B: "3:4",
C: "4:3",
D: "5:4",
answer: "B. 3:4",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. The demand curve for a necessity is usually",
A: "vertical.",
B: "backward bending,",
C: "horizontal.",
D: "negatively sloped.",
answer: "A. vertical.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. What effect will an increase in price have on the total revenue of a firm, whose product has inelastic demand? Total revenue will",
A: "increase.",
B: "fall",
C: "fluctuate.",
D: "remain unchanged.",
answer: "A. increase.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. If the quantity of men’s hats demanded per week is represented by the function Qd = 20 – 1/3p where p is price, how many hats are demanded when price is $ 9.00?",
A: "11",
B: "17",
C: "23",
D: "47",
answer: "B. 17",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. The demand for torch and batteries is an example of",
A: "competitive demand.",
B: "composite demand.",
C: "complementary demand.",
D: "derived demand.",
answer: "C. complementary demand.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. Price elasticity of supply measures how responsive",
A: "consumers are to a change in price.",
B: "sellers are to a change in buyers’ income.",
C: "sellers are to a change in price.",
D: "buyers are to a change in income.",
answer: "C. sellers are to a change in price.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. The tendency for workers to value their leisure hours more than hours of work as wage rate increases gives rise to",
A: "positively sloping supply curve.",
B: "perfectly elastic supply curve.",
C: "backward bending supply curve.",
D: "perfectly inelastic supply curve.",
answer: "C. backward bending supply curve.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. The supply of rice in tons is given by the function: Qs – 80 – 0.7P = 0. Where Qs = quantity supplied, P = price in Dollars ( 40.",
A: "108 tons.",
B: "52 tons.",
C: "– 52 tons.",
D: "-108 tons.",
answer: "A. 108 tons.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. How does producers’ expectation of a price fall affect the supply curve of a product? There will be",
A: "a movement along the curve.",
B: "a leftward shift.",
C: "no shift of the supply curve.",
D: "a shift to the right.",
answer: "B. a leftward shift.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. One relationship between marginal utility and total utility is that when total utility is",
A: "rising, marginal utility is rising.",
B: "falling, marginal utility is negative.",
C: "maximum, marginal utility is maximum.",
D: "falling, marginal utility is rising.",
answer: "B. falling, marginal utility is negative.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. A shift in the supply curve to the right while demand curve remains the same will cause equilibrium price",
A: "and quantity to fall.",
B: "and quantity to rise.",
C: "to rise and quantity to fall.",
D: "to fall and quantity to rise.",
answer: "C. to rise and quantity to fall.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. A price floor results in",
A: "excess demand.",
B: "excess supply.",
C: "parallel market.",
D: "hoarding of goods.",
answer: "B. excess supply.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. An entrepreneur is encouraged to adopt division of labour in production because it",
A: "provides more employment opportunities.",
B: "leads to increased output and lower cost of production.",
C: "brings about equal cost and employment opportunities.",
D: "leads to increased cost of production and lower output.",
answer: "B. leads to increased output and lower cost of production.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. The long run is a period when",
A: "only the variable factors can be altered.",
B: "all factors become variable.",
C: "the firm will cease to exist.",
D: "only the fixed factors can be altered.",
answer: "B. all factors become variable.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. The necessary condition for a firm to be in equilibrium is that marginal revenue is",
A: "greater than marginal cost.",
B: "equal to marginal cost.",
C: "less than average revenue.",
D: "equal to average cost.",
answer: "B. equal to marginal cost.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. At which stage of production should a firm shut down? When",
A: "AVC = ATC.",
B: "AVC < Price.",
C: "AVC > Price,",
D: "AVC = MC.",
answer: "C. AVC > Price, D. AVC = MC.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. Charging different prices for the same commodity is a feature of a",
A: "perfect competition.",
B: "commodity market.",
C: "monopolistic competition.",
D: "monopoly market.",
answer: "D. monopoly market.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. In a partnership, the conduct of members is guided by",
A: "a memorandum of understanding.",
B: "the articles of partnership.",
C: "an article of association.",
D: "a partnership constitution.",
answer: "D. a partnership constitution.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. Indigenization policy is a measure aimed at",
A: "privatizing the existing businesses owned by the state.",
B: "commercializing state-owned businesses.",
C: "reducing foreign economic domination.",
D: "making the indigenes managing directors of businesses.",
answer: "C. reducing foreign economic domination.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. Which of the following measures will hinder efficient distribution of goods in West Africa?",
A: "Improving road networks",
B: "Provision of adequate storage facilities",
C: "Instituting price control",
D: "Formation of producers’ co-operative societies",
answer: "C. Instituting price control",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. The type of unemployment that occurs as a result of physical or mental disability of labour is known as",
A: "frictional unemployment. >",
B: "structural unemployment.",
C: "cyclical unemployment",
D: "residual unemployment.",
answer: "D. residual unemployment.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. One feature of a growing population is",
A: "increase in the number of young people.",
B: "increase in the number of old people.",
C: "decrease in the dependent population,",
D: "decrease in the life expectancy.",
answer: "A. increase in the number of young people.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. Efficiency of labour in a country is determined by the following factors except the",
A: "social attitude to work.",
B: "education and training.",
C: "working conditions of workers.",
D: "total population.",
answer: "D. total population.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. Which of the following will encourage capital intensive farming?",
A: "Encouraging communal system of land ownership",
B: "Adopting policies that will encourage rural-urban migration",
C: "Provision of subsidies on equipment",
D: "Restrictive lending policies by banks",
answer: "C. Provision of subsidies on equipment",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. Which of the following best explains why more foreign investments are not attracted to West Africa?",
A: "Small population size",
B: "Small sizes of market places",
C: "Instability in political and industrial policies",
D: "Lack of manpower needed to work in industries",
answer: "C. Instability in political and industrial policies",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. Location of firms in rural areas may",
A: "enable the firms to enjoy existing infrastructural facilities.",
B: "make finance readily available.",
C: "enhance even or balanced development.",
D: "make such firms enjoy external economies of scale.",
answer: "C. enhance even or balanced development.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. In national income accounting, double counting occurs when",
A: "intermediate goods are counted twice.",
B: "intermediate goods are counted with the final goods.",
C: "final goods are counted more than once.",
D: "different people count the products.",
answer: "B. intermediate goods are counted with the final goods.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. The difference between GDP and GNP is",
A: "consumption of fixed capital.",
B: "indirect business taxes.",
C: "net factor income from abroad.",
D: "public transfer payments.",
answer: "C. net factor income from abroad.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. Which of the following items is not included in the measurement of the national income using the income approach?",
A: "Wages and salaries",
B: "Government purchases",
C: "Interest",
D: "Dividend",
answer: "B. Government purchases",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. A bank note is said to be a legal tender because it is",
A: "printed by government.",
B: "a store of value.",
C: "signed by the head of state.",
D: "backed by law.",
answer: "D. backed by law.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. During inflation, interest rates will",
A: "rise.",
B: "fluctuate.",
C: "remain constant.",
D: "fall.",
answer: "A. rise.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. Cost-push inflation is likely to arise when",
A: "there is an increase in bank lending.",
B: "there is an increase in subsidies.",
C: "demand for higher wages is granted.",
D: "there is a decrease in bank lending.",
answer: "C. demand for higher wages is granted.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. Which of the following financial institutions cannot be found on the capital market of a county?",
A: "Commercial bank",
B: "Mortgage bank",
C: "Stock exchange",
D: "Agricultural bank",
answer: "A. Commercial bank",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. The stock market is a market for",
A: "new and second hand shares.",
B: "debentures.",
C: "goods and services.",
D: "short-term securities.",
answer: "A. new and second hand shares.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. Indirect taxes are generally",
A: "progressive.",
B: "regressive.",
C: "equitable.",
D: "proportionate.",
answer: "B. regressive.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. Fiscal policy that can control inflation will include the use of",
A: "balanced budgeting.",
B: "tax holidays.",
C: "budget deficits.",
D: "budget surplus.",
answer: "D. budget surplus.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. Which of the following is a cause of underdevelopment in West Africa?",
A: "Availability of manpower",
B: "Increasing population",
C: "High rate of capital formation",
D: "Large size of market places",
answer: "B. Increasing population",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. Which of the following is not a major problem of development planning?",
A: "Shortage of skilled manpower",
B: "Inadequate data for planning",
C: "Political instability",
D: "Poor identification of projects",
answer: "D. Poor identification of projects",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. The principle of comparative cost advantage was propounded by",
A: "David Ricardo.",
B: "Alfred Marshall.",
C: "J. S. Mill.",
D: "Adam Smith.",
answer: "A. David Ricardo.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. The rate at which a country’s exports is exchanged for her imports is",
A: "trade balance.",
B: "balance of payments.",
C: "terms of trade.",
D: "balance on current account.",
answer: "C. terms of trade.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. Balance of payments surplus implies that receipts for exports are",
A: "at par with payments for imports.",
B: "greater than payments for imports.",
C: "less than payments for imports.",
D: "proportional to payments for imports.",
answer: "B. greater than payments for imports.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. When the international value of a country’s currency rises, other things being equal, the country’s",
A: "net exports tend to increase.",
B: "imports tend to decrease.",
C: "net exports tend to decrease.",
D: "exports tend to be stable.",
answer: "A. net exports tend to increase.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. One of the physical measures that can be used to reduce the volume of imports is the",
A: "reduction of personal income tax.",
B: "removal of import duties.",
C: "use of foreign exchange control.",
D: "liberalization of credit for importers.",
answer: "C. use of foreign exchange control.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. When a number of countries agree to remove all trade barriers among themselves and at the same time charge a common tariff against non-member countries, it is known as",
A: "free trade area.",
B: "common market,",
C: "customs union.",
D: "economic community.",
answer: "C. customs union.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. Which of the following international organizations is concerned with the stabilization of the balance of payments? The",
A: "International Monetary Fund (IMF)",
B: "World Bank (IBRD)",
C: "United Nations Organization (UNO)",
D: "Economic Commission for Africa (ECA)",
answer: "A. International Monetary Fund (IMF)",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},


]